<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Open-Source Python Tools for Annotation and
Classification of Marine Acoustic Backscattering</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0009-0003-4820-6999</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Ringuenet</surname>
<given-names>Gaspard</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Gaspard Ringuenet</string-name>

<email>gaspard.ringuenet@umontpellier.fr</email>
<role>Writiing</role>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="software" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="visualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Montpellier</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">gaspard.ringuenet@umontpellier.fr</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>


<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Multi-frequency acoustics</kwd>
<kwd>Machine Learning</kwd>
</kwd-group>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>1. Introduction</title>
  <p>We propose a set of open-source modular softwares for supervised
  echoclassification using traditional ML:</p>
  <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
      <p>A minimalist echogram annotation tool (using a new standard,
      Echoregions)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>A Jupyter notebook workflow class to post-process annotated
      regions and format output as ML-ready dataframe</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
      <p>Domain-specific ML tools sub-classing scikit-learn estimators
      and implementing and extending the Escore method</p>
    </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>As a demonstration we apply the Escore method to the ABRAÇOS
  campaigns data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="tools-description">
  <title>2. Tools description</title>
  <sec id="echolabel-image-based-echogram-annotation-tool">
    <title>2.1 <monospace>echolabel</monospace> image-based echogram
    annotation tool</title>
    <p>Echolabel is a minimalist Python application for interactive
    echogram annotation. It is based on a simple design: converting
    acoustic data into echogram images, and running an image annotation
    software with a graphical user interface (GUI) to draw polygonal
    shapes on those images. Our tool is free and open source, and
    enables fast echogram annotation at low computational cost. Online
    documentation is ongoing
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://echolabel.readthedocs.io/">https://echolabel.readthedocs.io/</ext-link>).</p>
    <p>It wraps LabelMe
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://labelme.io/">https://labelme.io/</ext-link>),
    is a popular image annotation software designed to build computer
    vision datasets, which was inspired by the Massachusetts Institute
    of Technology’s LabelMe web-based interface
    (<xref alt="Russell et al., 2008" rid="ref-russell2008" ref-type="bibr">Russell
    et al., 2008</xref>) and provides an open-source Python
    implementation with added features. LabelMe runs locally. Its key
    feature is a GUI built with PyQt5, allowing the user to draw shapes
    (namely polygons and lines) over the images. The application is run
    via its command line interface. Required arguments are source
    (acoustic data file(s)) and output (annotation file). Echogram
    visualization options can be specified, including mapped frequency
    channels and color mapping. Options can be provided as command line
    arguments or by editing the user’s configuration file, allowing
    pre-defined setup.</p>
    <p>When launched, the Echolabel reads the source data, chunks it
    into fixed-width frames, and saves each frame’s metadata in cache.
    Frames are then converted into images by scaling Sv, and applying a
    color mapping. Single frequency echograms can be printed using any
    matplotlib colormap. Three channels can be rendered simultaneously
    using an RGB mapping
    (<xref alt="Ariza et al., 2022" rid="ref-ariza2022" ref-type="bibr">Ariza
    et al., 2022</xref>), providing visual intuition on the organisms’
    frequency responses. Echogram images are saved in cache. If the
    output file already exists, it is read and converted into Labelme’s
    internal annotation format. The Labelme graphical user interface is
    then launched. As long as the window remains open, the user can add
    and edit shapes on the dataset’s images. When closing, shapes are
    converted to (time, depth) coordinates using cached images metadata
    and the annotation file is (over-)written. In case the output is
    overwritten, a copy of the pre-session file is stored as
    failsafe.</p>
    <p>As input acoustic data, Echolabel expects Echopype-like products
    i.e. gridded Sv data with “ping_time”, “depth” and “channel”
    dimensions, as well as “Sv” and “frequency_nominal” variables. Since
    Echopype’s format adapts ICES SONAR-netCDF4 convention
    (<xref alt="Macaulay &amp; Peña, 2018" rid="ref-macaulay2018" ref-type="bibr">Macaulay
    &amp; Peña, 2018</xref>), little to no conversion effort should be
    required to use Echolabel on standard acoustic datasets. One or more
    NetCDF files may be loaded depending on inter-file compatibility. A
    Zarr store is also accepted as input.</p>
    <p>Echolabel relies on Echoregions
    (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/echostack-org/echoregions">https://github.com/echostack-org/echoregions</ext-link>)
    to represent and parse polygonal echogram annotations. Echoregions
    is an interfacing package designed to represent acoustic data shapes
    annotations in Python and easily plug into machine learning (ML)
    pipelines. It is part of the Echostack suite
    (<xref alt="Lee et al., 2024" rid="ref-lee2024" ref-type="bibr">Lee
    et al., 2024</xref>). While still in development, it presents some
    key features which motivated using it to handle Echolabel’s
    annotations input-output, among which parsing and saving annotations
    in EchoView’s EVR file formats in addition to CSV files. This
    feature enables Echolabel’s output files to be converted to EVR
    format easily. Further development of Echoregions should extend
    compatibility to other echogram annotation formats
    (<xref alt="Lee et al., 2024" rid="ref-lee2024" ref-type="bibr">Lee
    et al., 2024</xref>). Another functionality is converting
    annotations to machine learning ready masks (annotation to ML) and
    generating annotation from ML predictions (ML to annotation).
    Annotation to ML is the primary use case of Echolabel. Converting
    echograms to images comes at a cost: losing time and depth label,
    enforcing a 1:1 aspect ratio for sampled volumes, having no access
    to the numeric values of pixels. However, many annotation tasks can
    still be performed efficiently (identifying and delineating
    aggregations, or finding regions of interest for the Escore
    algorithm). Besides, image files are much lighter than original
    data, and their rendering is optimized by LabelMe. This enables fast
    scrolling through the echogram, and eventually improves user
    experience and processing speed. A current limitation, however, is
    LabelMe’s default smoothing behaviour. This blurs the signal at a
    small scale when zooming and is problematic when looking for the
    edge of an echogram feature. Echolabel currently deletes shapes that
    span more than one echogram image. This is an issue when editing
    annotation files made with a different software or image width.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="extractionworkflow-annotation-to-ml-tool">
    <title>2.2 <monospace>ExtractionWorkflow</monospace>
    annotation-to-ML tool</title>
    <p>Once a set of echogram regions has been defined and stored as an
    annotation file, using those within an ML pipeline requires
    extracting the samples and assembling them as a dataframe.
    Additionally, because of high pixel-wise variability in acoustic
    response, delineating echogram features with polygons is often not
    sufficient to catch the desired signal. Post-processing of regions,
    for instance using frequency response clustering, can be necessary
    to extract complex objects or reduce signal variability. Such a
    treatment requires close supervision by the operator in order to
    select meaningful data. The ExtractionWorkflow class provides a
    framework and utilities for the post-processing of region data.
    Parametrized by an acoustic dataset and the corresponding region
    annotations (<monospace>Regions2D</monospace> object), it allows the
    user to loop through all regions, perform a segmentation task, and
    save or reject the result. Built to be used in a Jupyter notebook,
    the workflow class also enables rich visualization of input and
    results during processing. Plots include echograms and frequency
    response statistics. Leveraging the hvplot library enables
    interactive plots.</p>
    <p>The core objective of the workflow is selecting a subset of each
    region. This is done using a “segmenter”. The segmenter is a
    scikit-learn Pipeline instance, using the region’s channel dimension
    as features. While we show the use of our own model in the example
    section, the user is allowed to set their own segmenter depending on
    their extraction goals.</p>
    <p>The workflow object stores the segmentation results and recipes
    (segmentation model, selected segment) as files, enabling full
    reproducibility of the interactive process. Processed regions are
    tracked in the state YAML file. Processing state can be accessed
    using the <monospace>status_report</monospace> method. Once the user
    is satisfied with the processed regions, all samples can be exported
    as a dataframe for further use in ML pipelines.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="escore-broad-ecosystem-semi-supervised-thresholding-package">
    <title>2.3 <monospace>escore</monospace> broad-ecosystem
    semi-supervised thresholding package</title>
    <sec id="api-description">
      <title>2.3.1 API description</title>
    </sec>
    <sec id="svs-algorithm">
      <title>2.3.2 SVS algorithm</title>
      <p>Algorithm description (Gary Vargas’ flow chart) Module
      features.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="escore-model">
      <title>2.3.3 Escore model</title>
      <p><bold>Motivation and introduction</bold></p>
      <p>The Ellipsoïd score (Escore) method is a dB-differencing method
      introduced by Annasawmy et al.
      (<xref alt="2024" rid="ref-annasawmy2024" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>).
      It is a generalization of the Z-score
      (<xref alt="De Robertis et al., 2010" rid="ref-derobertis2010" ref-type="bibr">De
      Robertis et al., 2010</xref>) for more than 2 frequencies.
      Besides, the Escore is adapted to the lack of easily separable
      aggregation and the sparsity of trawling coverage by relying on
      RGB composite echogram scrutinizing.</p>
      <p>The method was originally split into 6 steps. <italic>Step
      1</italic>: using RGB echogram, identify regions of interest
      (ROI), each containing a structure of interest with homogeneous
      frequency responses. <italic>Step 2</italic>: use KMeans
      clustering of ΔMVBS to select a subset of each ROI, discarding
      inconsistent signal. The selected “clean” cluster is called an
      echo-type. <italic>Step 3</italic>: cluster echo-type into
      echo-classes using their mean frequency response. <italic>Step
      4</italic>: If an echo-class’ dominant frequency is unique (not
      shared by another echoclass), define having this dominant
      frequency as a classification rule for this echo-class.
      <italic>Step 5</italic> (fitting the Escore model): For all other
      echo-classes, aggregate echotypes samples, and compute their means
      and covariances in ΔMVBS space. For any echo-integrated cell i and
      echo-class k, Escore(i, k) is defined as the squared-Mahalanobis
      distance of i to distribution k in ΔMVBS space. Cell i is
      classified in the echo-class with the lowest Escore, except if
      this minimum is above a given threshold. <italic>Step 6</italic>:
      Predict on a full acoustic dataset. See for Annasawmy et al.
      (<xref alt="2024" rid="ref-annasawmy2024" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)
      a more detailed explanation.</p>
      <p><bold>Our implementation</bold></p>
      <p>Our package implements the Escore method in Python with some
      modifications. In a modular approach, the user is left to complete
      step 1 with the echogram annotation of his choice, as long as the
      annotation format can be read as a
      <monospace>Regions2D</monospace> object. The
      <monospace>ExtractionWorkflow</monospace> can then be used to
      extract echo-types using KMeans as a segmenter with a
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\Delta \text{MVBS}]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">MVBS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      transform (completing step 2). In a very similar manner, step 3
      can be achieved using the scikit-learn framework. We only provide
      simple utility functions to inspect and evaluate clustering
      performance. With regards to the model itself, we propose some
      changes. To begin with, we dropped step 4, unsure of the
      additional benefits compared to applying step 5 to all
      echoclasses.</p>
      <p>We designed a custom scikit-learn estimator called
      <monospace>EscoreClassifier</monospace>. In a slight change from
      the original description, we re-interpreted the Escore model as a
      combination of Gaussian distributions in
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\Delta \text{MVBS}]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">MVBS</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      space, one for each echo-class. Learning this supervised model
      comes down to learning the parameters of those distributions,
      i.e. still the echo-classes’ means and covariance matrices. The
      model can then predict the Mahalanobis distance of a given point
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[x]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      to each distribution. That distance can in turn be used to compute
      the likelihood of <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\mathbb{P}(x|c)]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      for any echo-class <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[c]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.
      This probabilistic formulation adds some interpretability to an
      otherwise abstract distance measure. One could also want to derive
      the posterior probabilities <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[\mathbb{P}(c|x)]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
      but this is out of this work’s scope.</p>
      <p>In addition to learned parameters, our model is also defined by
      two hyper parameters corresponding to prediction thresholds. The
      first one is equivalent to the original Escore threshold. It
      defined the minimal likelihood for prediction. The second one is a
      quality threshold controlling the maximum acceptable ratio of
      likelihoods between the best and second best class. This avoids
      predicting at the boundaries between echo-classes, which might be
      welcome in some cases.</p>
      <p>As a mathematical formulation, we consider a set of echoclasses
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[C]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
      and we assume that the conditional probability distribution of
      each echoclass follows a normal distribution:</p>
      <p><disp-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[
      \forall c \in C, \mathbb{P}(.|c) \sim \mathcal{N}(\mu_c, \Sigma_c)
      ]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="block" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:mi>𝒩</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Assuming an <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[n]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>-dimensional
      ΔMVBS space and <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[x \in \mathbb{R}^n]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℝ</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>,
      the best and second best echoclass predictions for
      <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[x]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      can be defined as:</p>
      <p><disp-formula><tex-math><![CDATA[
      \DeclareMathOperator*{\argmax}{arg\,max}
      c_1 = \argmax_c{\mathbb{P}(x|c)} \\
      c_2 = \argmax_{c \neq c_1}{\mathbb{P}(x|c)}
      ]]></tex-math></disp-formula></p>
      <p>Our model is the prediction function f such that:</p>
      <p><disp-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[
      f(x) = \left\{ \begin{array}{l}
      -1 & : \mathbb{P}(x|c_1) < e_{\text{thresh}} \ \cup \ \mathbb{P}(x|c_2) / \mathbb{P}(x|c_1) >  q_{\text{thresh}}\\
      c_1 & : else
      \end{array} \right.
      ]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="block" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left" style="text-align: left"><mml:mi>−</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">thresh</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.222em"></mml:mspace><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.222em"></mml:mspace><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>/</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℙ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="prefix">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false" form="postfix">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="normal">thresh</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left" style="text-align: left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center" style="text-align: center"><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p>
      <p>where <inline-formula><alternatives>
      <tex-math><![CDATA[-1]]></tex-math>
      <mml:math display="inline" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>−</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>
      is a rejection value returned when the thresholds constraints are
      violated.</p>
      <p>Integrating into the scikit-learn API brings some notable
      benefits. In particular, this unlocks support for cross validation
      and a wide range of other machine learning utilities.</p>
    </sec>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="case-study-echoclassification-in-high-diversity-context">
  <title>3. Case-study: echoclassification in high diversity
  context</title>
  <sec id="data">
    <title>3.1 Data</title>
    <p>Two oceanographic surveys, ABRAÇOS I and ABRAÇOS II, were
    performed in the Southwest tropical Atlantic in Austral spring 2015
    (September 29-October 21) and fall 2017 (April 9-March 8), as part
    of the project ‘Acoustics along the Brazilian coast’
    (<xref alt="Bertrand, 2015" rid="ref-bertrand2015" ref-type="bibr">Bertrand,
    2015</xref>,
    <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-bertrand2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
    The study area encompassed the continental shelf and slope off
    Northeast Brazil, and oceanic waters around the islands and
    seamounts of the Fernando de Noronha Chain.</p>
    <p>Acoustic transects were conducted perpendicularly over the
    continental slope, and radially around the Rocas Atoll and the
    Fernando de Noronha Archipelago 1. Acoustic data were collected with
    a SIMRAD EK60 echosounder at 38, 70, 120 and 200 kHz, synchronously
    transmitting every 2-3 s. Volume backscattering strength ‘Sv’ (dB re
    1 m-1)
    (<xref alt="Maclennan et al., 2002" rid="ref-maclennan2002" ref-type="bibr">Maclennan
    et al., 2002</xref>) was recorded down to 700 m depth with a pulse
    duration of 512 μs, beam angle of 7°, and a transmit power of 1000,
    750 and 200 W at 38, 70 and 120 kHz, respectively. Standard target
    calibration of the echosounder was conducted prior to data
    acquisition
    (<xref alt="Demer et al., 2015" rid="ref-demer2015" ref-type="bibr">Demer
    et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="references">
    <title>References</title>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref-ariza2022">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Ariza</surname><given-names>Alejandro</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lebourges-Dhaussy</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Nerini</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Pauthenet</surname><given-names>Etienne</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Roudaut</surname><given-names>Gildas</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Assunção</surname><given-names>Ramilla</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Tosetto</surname><given-names>Everton</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>Arnaud</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acoustic seascape partitioning through functional data analysis</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Biogeography</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022-11-23">2022</year><month>11</month><day>23</day>
          <uri>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jbi.14534</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jbi.14534</pub-id>
          <fpage>jbi.14534</fpage>
          <lpage></lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-russell2008">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>Bryan C.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Torralba</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>Kevin P.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>William T.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>LabelMe: A database and web-based tool for image annotation</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Computer Vision</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2008-05-01">2008</year><month>05</month><day>01</day>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11263-007-0090-8</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11263-007-0090-8</pub-id>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-lee2024">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Wu-Jung</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Staneva</surname><given-names>Valentina</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Setiawan</surname><given-names>Landung “Don”</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Mayorga</surname><given-names>Emilio</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Tuguinay</surname><given-names>Caesar</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Butala</surname><given-names>Soham</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lucca</surname><given-names>Brandyn</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Dingrui</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Echostack: A flexible and scalable open-source software suite for echosounder data processing</article-title>
          <source>Python in Science Conference</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2024-06-03">2024</year><month>06</month><day>03</day>
          <uri>https://proceedings.scipy.org/articles/WXRH8633</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25080/WXRH8633</pub-id>
          <fpage>386</fpage>
          <lpage>397</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-macaulay2018">
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>Gavin</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Peña</surname><given-names>Hector</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The SONAR-netCDF4 convention for sonar data, version 1.0</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2018-05-01">2018</year><month>05</month><day>01</day>
          <uri>https://ices-library.figshare.com/articles/report/The_SONAR-netCDF4_convention_for_sonar_data_Version_1_0/18624056/1</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17895/ices.pub.4392</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-annasawmy2024">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Annasawmy</surname><given-names>Pavanee</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Roudaut</surname><given-names>Gildas</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lebourges-Dhaussy</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of an eddy dipole of the mozambique channel on mesopelagic organisms, highlighted by multifrequency backscatter classification</article-title>
          <source>PLOS ONE</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2024-09-11">2024</year><month>09</month><day>11</day>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <uri>https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0309840</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0309840</pub-id>
          <fpage>e0309840</fpage>
          <lpage></lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-derobertis2010">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>De Robertis</surname><given-names>Alex</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>McKelvey</surname><given-names>Denise R.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Ressler</surname><given-names>Patrick H.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development and application of an empirical multifrequency method for backscatter classification</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010-09">2010</year><month>09</month>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <uri>https://cdnsciencepub.com/doi/full/10.1139/F10-075</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/F10-075</pub-id>
          <fpage>1459</fpage>
          <lpage>1474</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-bertrand2015">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>Gildas AND Lebourges-Dhaussy</given-names><suffix>Arnaud AND Roudaut</suffix></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ABRACOS 1 cruise. Acoustic data</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name><surname>SEANOE</surname></name>
          </person-group>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.17882/77035</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17882/77035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-bertrand2017">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>Gildas AND Lebourges-Dhaussy</given-names><suffix>Arnaud AND Roudaut</suffix></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ABRACOS 2 cruise. Acoustic data</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name><surname>SEANOE</surname></name>
          </person-group>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.17882/91135</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17882/91135</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-maclennan2002">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Maclennan</surname><given-names>David N.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Paul G.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Dalen</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A consistent approach to definitions and symbols in fisheries acoustics</article-title>
          <source>ICES Journal of Marine Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2002-01-01">2002</year><month>01</month><day>01</day>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.1006/jmsc.2001.1158</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmsc.2001.1158</pub-id>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>369</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-demer2015">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name><surname>Demer</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Bernasconi</surname><given-names>Matteo</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Bethke</surname><given-names>Eckhard</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Boswell</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Dezhang</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Domokos</surname><given-names>Reka</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Dunford</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Fassler</surname><given-names>Sascha</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>Stephane</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Hufnagle</surname><given-names>Lawrence T.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Jech</surname><given-names>J. Michael</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Bouffant</surname><given-names>Naigle</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lebourges-Dhaussy</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Lurton</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Macaulay</surname><given-names>Gavin J.</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Perrot</surname><given-names>Yannick</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Parker-Stetter</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Stienessen</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
            <name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>Neal</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calibration of acoustic instruments.</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <uri>https://repository.oceanbestpractices.org/handle/11329/626</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
</back>



</article>